<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to the late King James's declaration to all his pretended subjects in the Kingdom of England, dated at Dublin-Castle May 8, 1689</title>
            <author>Welwood, James, 1652-1727.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65410</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1299</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24610</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08254197</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08254197</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41218</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65410)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41218)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1243:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to the late King James's declaration to all his pretended subjects in the Kingdom of England, dated at Dublin-Castle May 8, 1689</title>
                  <author>Welwood, James, 1652-1727.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  II, --  King of England, 1633-1701.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702 --  Pamphlets.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb facs="tcp:41218:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41218:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER TO THE Late King <hi>JAMES</hi>'s Declaration To all his pretended Subjects in the Kingdom of England.</head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>Dated at <hi>Dublin-Caſtle,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>May</hi> 8. 1689.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Publiſhed according to Order.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>WHEN one reflects upon the continued Conduct of the Late King <hi>James,</hi> both before and after his Acceſſion to the Crown, and the diſmal Conſequences thereof to theſe Three Kingdoms, and at laſt to himſelf, I cannot but regrate the Fate of thoſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that abandon their true Intereſt, Reaſon, Conſcience and Honour, to <hi>Jeſuitick</hi> Councils, and enſlave themſelves to a Party, juſtly abominated by the better part of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church it ſelf, for their groſs Encroachments upon Religion, Morality, and all that's Sacred among men. When I look back to the many Tragedies acted by that Fraternity, both in this, and the laſt Age, ſcarce a Kingdom of State in <hi>Europe,</hi> where their Villanies have not come up to the utmoſt reach of depraved Nature: When I call to mind the Horrid Deſolations, Murders and Wars, they have been Inſtrumental of, in the moſt remote parts of the World; wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſome Millions of Souls is <hi>Japan,</hi> and other parts of <hi>Aſia,</hi> ſacrificed not many Years ago, to their Ambition and Intrigues, under the Notion of propagating the Catholick Faith; I ſay, when I confider all there things, I am the leſs ſurprized with the diſmal Effects of their Councils in <hi>England,</hi> ſince the ſame Fate attends them every where. But <hi>I</hi> muſt confeſs, That among all the Martyrs to <hi>Loyola</hi>'s Principles, there is none more juſtly claims our Compaſſion, than the Late King <hi>James.</hi> To ſee a Prince, naturally of no bad Temper, Impoſed upon by theſe zealous Bigots, to trample upon the Religion and Liberties of His People, contrary to Fundamental Laws, and the moſt ſolemn Promiſes and Oaths, under the falſe Mask of piety and Zeal to the Catholick Faith, and at length to find him ſeduc'd to abandon His Kingdoms, and thereby an abſolute neceſſity put upon the Repreſentatives of the People, to fill up His Throne, vacated by His own Fault, is a Subject that naturally diſplays the vanity of human Greatneſs. And I may add, That the unaccountable Doctrine of <hi>Paſſive-Obedience,</hi> as it was the Source of a great many Miſchiefs among our ſelves, ſo what has befallen that King, may be partly imputed to it; for believing, That without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troul he might do what he pleaſ'd, encourag'd him to take ſuch meaſures as have brought upon him all his Misfortunes, I cannot but at the ſame time repreſent to my ſelf, with that emotion of mind the affrighted Paſſenger looks back upon the devour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Billows he has lately eſcap'd, the diſmal Scene of Ruin that ſo lately threatned us, and that Abyſs of Miſery we had certainly been plung'd into e're now, if his preſent Majeſty had not opportunely delivered us from the very Jaws of Death and Ruin.</p>
            <p>That any of the Proteſtant Perſwaſion at home, ſhould be found Repiners at this
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41218:2"/>mighty deliverance, is in my humble opinion, an unaccountable place of Ingratitude and Weakneſs at once; When all the Reformed States abroad, look upon this great Revolution in <hi>Brittain,</hi> as the moſt happy Providence that has appear'd on the Theatre of <hi>Europe</hi> this Century of Years. The late mighty Enterprize of His Majeſty, was the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult of the united Conſultations of all the Foreign Proteſtant States and Princes in this part of <hi>Chriſtendom;</hi> who ſettled upon it, as the laſt Caſt of the Dyce, for their Religion and Liberty; and with a trembling Expectation, made Vows to Almighty God, for the Succeſs of an Attempt, they wiſely forſaw, carried in its Womb the Fate, not only of theſe Three Kingdoms, but of all the Reformed Churches of <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When Heaven laid ſmil'd upon this ſtupendious Attempt, and had beyond the uſual Tract of Providence, vouchſafed us a Deliverance ſcarce equal'd in the Records of Time, Who would have imagin'd that <hi>England</hi> ſhould produce ſuch a ſort of Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, as ſeem to be in love with Slavery and Ruin, the neceſſary Conſequences of their unhappy Wretches, that have ſo induſtriouſly diſperſ'd through this great City, that Paper called, <hi>King</hi> James <hi>His Declaration to all His Loving Subjects in the Kingdom of</hi> England: A Paper, I could have wiſh'd for King <hi>James</hi>'s own Honour had been buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Eternal Oblivion, ſince it contains a heap of Falſities, that was below a Prince to affirm, and which are known to be ſo, by no fewer than the people of Three Kingdoms. In giving my Reflections upon this Declaration, the Reſpect due to one that was lately a Crowned Head, with ſome other juſt motives; obliges me to do it with more reſervedneſs than perhaps ſuch a Paper deſerves; and in ſtead of a needleſs expoſing a Prince, that has his Honour too much ſunk already, in the eyes of all <hi>Europe,</hi> I ſhall with all the Calmneſs and Candor poſſible, examine the Declaration it ſelf, without Reflections upon the Prince whoſe it is; and ſhall not omit one ſingle Sentence in it, that can be interpreted even by Himſelf, of any Conſequence.</p>
            <p>Thus His Declaration begins, <hi>Altho the many Calumnies and diſmal Stories, by which Our Enemies have endeavoured to render Us and Our Government odious to the World, do now appear to have been advanc'd by them, not only without any ground but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their own certain knowledge; as is evident by their not daring to attempt the prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe Charges to the World, which we cannot but hope, hath opened the eyes of Our good Subjects, to ſee how they have been impoſed upon by deſigning men, who to promote their own Ambitious Ends, care not what Slavery they reduce Our Kingdoms to.</hi> It ſeems King <hi>James</hi> continues in His wonted road, of taking wrong meaſures both of Perſons and Actions, which has been the occaſion of all His Miſfortunes. When he talks of his Enemies, that have rendred him and his Government odious to the World, He miſtakes himſelf, if he means thoſe Worthy Patriots, that being weary of his inſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable Incroachments upon the Religious and Civil Liberties of theſe Nations, did lend a hand, to deliver themſelves and Fellow ſubjects from a Ruin that ſeem'd almoſt inevitable. But if He had been at the pains to make an impartial Survey of his own Actings, and the pernicious Counſels of a ſort of Men about him. He might eaſily come to know, That His only and real Enemies were thoſe Popiſh Emiſſaries, that valued not how much His Honour ſuffer'd, nor his Crown were indanger'd, if ſo be they might bring about their own hidden Deſigns; and were willing to ſacrifice both Him, and His Intereſt, to their own by ends. Never Prince was ſo unhappy in His Cabinet-Council as He; and that <hi>falſe light</hi> which led Him to imploy none about Him, with any intimacy of confidence, but thoſe of His own Perſwaſion, prov'd an <hi>ignis fatuus,</hi> than cheated Him into paths never trode by any of His Predeceſſors but to their deſtruction. If he had been ſo happy, as to have continued in His moſt Secret Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils a great many Perſons of the Reform'd Religion, whom he kept at a diſtance,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:41218:2"/>though to amuſe the Nation He allowed them the empty Names of Privy Counſelors; He had not brought three Kingdoms to the brink of Ruine, nor upon Himſelf ſo hard a fate. Yet I muſt acknowledge ſome part of the obligation we have to theſe Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, that of late had the ſole conduct of King <hi>JAMES</hi> His Affairs; For in giving Him ſuch Counſels as his greateſt Enemies could have wiſh'd Him, they prov'd the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of our being at this day happy under the Auſpicious Reign of their Majeſties, being Princes of the ſame Religion and Intereſts with Their People; And we may juſtly ſay, as <hi>Themistocles</hi> of old, <hi>we had undoubtedly periſh'd, if we had not periſh'd.</hi> How little is King <hi>James</hi> oblig'd to His Secretary that penn'd this Deelaration, ſince he ſo fooliſhly rakes up the Remembrance of thoſe things that made Him and His Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment odious to the World, by the names of Calumnies and Stories, which it was ſo much His Maſter's Intereſt to bury in ſilence? Good God! Were the late palpable and barefac'd Incroachments upon the Fundamental Laws of the Nation, but Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies? Were the open Violations of Solemn Oaths, Promiſes and Ingagements, but Stories? Does King <hi>James,</hi> or His <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> Councellors imagine, that we have ſo ſoon forgot His <hi>Promiſes made in Council</hi> not many hours after His Brother's Death, and his compicuous Breaches of them not many months thereafter? Can we allow our ſelves to forget, that all the Truſts both in <hi>Court, Bench, and the Army,</hi> were filled up with theſe very Men, whom Reiterated Laws had rendred incapable of them? Was a <hi>Perſon's ſitting at the Council board,</hi> whoſe very being found in <hi>England</hi> was death by the Law, but a meer Calumny? Can a few months be able to obliterate the Memory of that Affair of <hi>Megdalen Colledge,</hi> one of the moſt open Invaſions of Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that could be? Have we loſt the Remembrance of that Illegal <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Court,</hi> and the Tyrannick Judgments paſt therein? Have we not ſeen a <hi>Reverend Prelat</hi> ſuſpended from his Function, meerly becauſe he would not do what he could not, that is, for not condemning a man unheard? Have not we ſeen ſeven of the <hi>Spiritual Peers</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> ſent priſoners to the <hi>Tower,</hi> and brought as Criminals to the Bar, for barely repreſenting the Reaſons, why they could not obey an Arbitrary Command, contrary to their Conſcience? Both <hi>England,</hi> and our Neighbouring Nation have too many Reaſons, to remember the Late King <hi>James</hi>'s aſſuming to himſelf an <hi>Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary and Deſpotick Power,</hi> not only to diſpence with Laws, and the firmeſt Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but to act diametrically oppoſite to them. Can King <hi>James</hi>'s Oratory perſwade us, That the continuing to Levy the <hi>Cuſtoms and additional Exciſe,</hi> (which had been only granted during the Late King <hi>Charles</hi>'s Life) before the Parliament could meet to renew this Grant, was but a Calumny? Was the ſtrange Eſſay of <hi>Mahome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan Government,</hi> acted at <hi>Taunton</hi> and <hi>Lyme;</hi> and the no leſs ſtrange Proceedings of that Bloody Chief Juſtice, in his Weſtern Circuit, (juſtly term'd <hi>his Champaign,</hi> for it was an open Hoſtility to all Law) for which, and the like Services, he had the reward of the Great Seal, were they all but Stories? We have too good Reaſon not to forget the many Violences committed by the Soldiers of a ſtanding Army in moſt Parts of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> which are the moſt ſevere and inſupportable Invaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Property.</p>
            <p>Theſe, and ſuch like, with a great many more, were the things that render'd King <hi>James</hi>'s Government Juſtly <hi>Odious to the</hi> Britiſh <hi>world,</hi> and made theſe three Kingdoms groan after Liberty. If ſo grave and tragick a Subject, could allow it. <hi>I</hi> could be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt tempted to laugh at that Expreſſion in the Declaration, of his Enemies not dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to attempt the proving theſe Charges to the World; which is all one, as if a Man in the ſevereſt fit of the Gout, ſhould be deſir'd to prove that he is ſo, when the Senſe of the Pain proves too ſad a remembrancer of his Diſtemper. And indeed, this part of King <hi>James's</hi> Declaration merits no other anſwer, than that of the <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41218:3"/>him who deny'd motion, When making a ſtep up and down the Room, he vouchſaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him no other Refutation of his Ridiculous Aſſertion, than theſe two words, <hi>hiene Motus?</hi> In fine, It will be equally impoſſible to perſwade the World, that theſe Actions, that tender'd King <hi>James's</hi> Government <hi>Odious to the world,</hi> were but Calumnies and Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, as to perſwade a Man upon the Rack, that he feels no pain. How unluckily have the Penners of his Declaration, ſtumbled upon that Expreſſion, <hi> of his Enemies not caring what Slavery they reduce the Kingdoms to? Quis tulerit Gracch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s?</hi> That King <hi>James</hi> had in a great meaſure, enſlav'd theſe Nations, and was upon the Ripen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his deſigns, in Conjunction with <hi>Lewis</hi> the 14th. to teach us a <hi>French kind of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection,</hi> has appear'd in legible Characters, by the whole Scheme of his Actings: But ſince his preſent Majeſties Acceſſion to the Throne, there is not the leaſt footſtep of Slavery left us; we are bleſt with a King that takes the Advice of his Parliament, and owns to diſtinct Intereſt from that of his People; a Prince, who to deliver us from Popery and Slavery, has ventur'd his <hi>All,</hi> and who by his Conduct at home, and his Allies abroad, is capable to render us happy, If our own Diviſions and Folly do not precipitate us into an inevitable and unpitied Ruin.</p>
            <p>In the next place, King <hi>James</hi> tells us, <hi>That ſince his Arrival in</hi> Ireland, <hi>the Defence of his Protestant Subjects</hi> (as he calls them) <hi>their Religion, Priviledges and Properties, is eſpecially his care, with the Recovery of his own Rights. And to this end, he has pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd ſuch of them, of whoſe Loyalty and affection he is ſatisfied to places both of the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Honour and Truſt about his Perſon, as well as in his Army.</hi> The Reading of theſe Lines puts me in mind of the parallel, ſo exactly obſerv'd betwixt the <hi>French</hi> King and King <hi>James,</hi> in all their Conduct, and particularly in both their way of aſſerting the calm Methods uſed by them towards their Proteſtant Subjects. When that <hi>Common Enemy of the Christian part of</hi> Europe (as the preſent Pope was pleaſed to call him) had outdone all the <hi>Nero's,</hi> and <hi>Julian</hi>'s of old, in the Art of Perſecution, and had render'd himſelf abominated to the World, by the Cruelties committed by his Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goon Miſſioners upon thoſe very people that had done him the beſt Offices, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved the Crown upon his Head in this Minority; yet at the very ſame time, <hi>Lewis</hi> the 14th, and his Miniſters, have had the Impudence to affirm, That no other Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods were us'd to Convert theſe poor Victims, but thoſe of fair Perſuaſion and Calm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Juſt ſo King <hi>James,</hi> that he may follow as near his Copy as poſſible, having ſince his Arrival in <hi>Ireland,</hi> abandoned the Proteſtants of that Countrey to the Mercileſs Rage of an Enemy irreconcilable, from both a principle of Religion and Civil Intereſt, who within his view had laid deſolate whole Counties, and acted Barbarities proper only to themſelves, and their <hi>French</hi> Confederats; and by which they have forc'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way a great many Thouſands from their Countrey, at the point of Starving, having ſav'd nothing of their Fortunes from ſo univerſal a Calamity. Yet, no withſtanding all this appears in the Face of the Sun, King <hi>James,</hi> that he may not come ſhort of his Patron, boldly affirms, That the Religion, Priviledges and Properties of his Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Subjects (as he names them) are his chiefeſt Care ever and above. What a groſs Contradiction is it to common Senſe and Reaſon, that a Prince bigotted to the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion, and enſlav'd to Jeſuitick Councils, ſhould make that Religion, which in his Opinion, is an <hi>execrable Hereſy,</hi> become his <hi>equal Care,</hi> with what he calls the <hi>Recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his Right?</hi> Sure I am, in this Expreſſion he has mightily overacted his part, and nothing but a belief capable to receive <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> can be perſwaded of the fair meaning of it. If the propoſition could poſſibly admit of favourable Conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, then it muſt neceſſarily follow, That King <hi>James</hi> is of another Communion than that of <hi>Rome,</hi> which were a great injury done him to ſuppoſe, ſeing he has given us ſuch convincing proofs to the contrary: For every <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick is obliged to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41218:3"/>look upon the Proteſtants as <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and their Religion as <hi>Hereſy;</hi> and we have once every year the <hi>imaginary Succeſſor of Saint</hi> Peter, formally Curſing us in perſon; and from his plenary power, declaring us to be fallen from all our Civil Rights. If King <hi>James</hi> had ſaid, the Proteſtants are his Care, meaning the Converſion of them to his Religion, by the calm methods of a Dragoon Miſſion, he would have found no great difficulty to have been believ'd. But to affirm that, <hi>That peſtilent Northern Hereſy,</hi> the the Proteſtant Religion, <hi>was his Care,</hi> is, indeed a ſtretch beyond the ordinary pitch of Jeſuitick Equivocation it ſelf. We have had occaſion enough to be acquainted with the charity of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> towards thoſe of our Religion; it has been both fervent and burning: And leſt we ſhould forget what has been done in former Ages, <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Savoy</hi> have of late ſet before us new Inſtances of the Charity of that Church. No doubt King <hi>James</hi>'s ſincerity in this aſſertion, <hi>is</hi> the ſame with that of all his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes: And, albeit when he was upon the Throne, we were told in ſome of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations, That we were bound to obey <hi>without reſerve;</hi> It's hardſhip upon hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to be oblig'd, now when he is juſtly Abdicated to <hi>believe without reſerve.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, that we may the eaſier be perſuaded of King <hi>James</hi>'s care of the Proteſtants of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and their properties, let us take a ſhort glance of the great favours he has be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on them, ſince his Arrival there. One would think, that a Mans's <hi>Eſtate, his Houſe, Furniture, his Arms, Money, Chattels, and the like,</hi> were included under the word <hi>Property:</hi> King <hi>James</hi> his care has been ſo tranſcendently great of this ſort of Property, that there are at this day, in <hi>England</hi> and the Neighbouring Nations, Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Gentlemen, Clergy, Merchants, and Tradeſmen, whoſe Eſtates, ſeiz'd upon by King <hi>James</hi>'s Order, amounts to no more than four Million of pounds <hi>Sterling:</hi> If any doubt of the Truth of this, I refer them to Liſt and Account, taken of the <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh</hi> Proteſtants by the Commiſſioners appointed by the King for that effect. Neither is there, at preſent, one ſingle Proteſtant within that Kingdom, that can rationally aſſure himſelf of one moments poſſeſſion of what the Barbarous <hi>Iriſh</hi> has left them yet undeſtroyed. Who knows not, That upon weighty Reaſons, the Wiſdom of the Kings of <hi>England</hi> thought it very dangerous to truſt the Natives of <hi>Ireland</hi> with Arms, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from many funeſt Experiences, they were a people impatient of the <hi>Engliſh Yoke,</hi> and ready to accept all occaſions to throw it off<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But King <hi>James</hi> treads quite another path; in ſtead of diſ-arming theſe his <hi>darling Wild Iriſh,</hi> they are the only people he can truſt, as knowing their furious Zeal to his Religion, and their Hereditary hatred to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, renders them fit Inſtruments to execute the deſigns concerted betwixt him and his intimate Allie, the <hi>French</hi> King: And which, to capacitate them the better to effectuate, he has wiſely diſarmed before hand, the whole Proteſtants of that Kingdom, and prepared them ready Victims for their Bloody Enemies, when ever it ſhall be time to give the blow. I confeſs, it requires the greateſt ſtock of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, to hear one boldly affirm his care of my life, and at the ſame time to ſee him give me up, bound and de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enceleſs, into the hands of my cruel and mortal Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
            <p>There is another tranſcendent Inſtance of King <hi>James</hi>'s <hi>Care of the Proteſtants in</hi> Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>their Religion, and Property,</hi> which merits to be engraven in <hi>Corinthian</hi> Braſs to poſterity. All that are in the leaſt acquainted with the Laws and Affairs of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, know, that the <hi>Act of Settlement</hi> is the great Security of the Proteſtants, their Religion and properties, and the Fundamental Right they have to their Eſtates, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer'd from the Rebellious Iriſh, at the expence of their Blood and Treaſure. <hi>By</hi> this <hi>Act,</hi> the <hi>laſting Landmarks</hi> are fixt among the Proteſtants themſelves, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them and the Natives. This is indeed the <hi>Magna Charta</hi> of the Proteſtants of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the true <hi>Baſis</hi> of their Liberties and Properties; upon the taking away of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41218:4"/>which, the Superſtructure muſt tumble to the ground. Now King <hi>James</hi>'s <hi>Care of the Proteſtants</hi> is of ſo high a nature, that in his firſt Speech to his <hi>Mock-parliament,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting all of Papiſts (except about five or ſix) <hi>May</hi> 7. he aſſures them, <hi>He would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the enacting ſuch Laws as might relieve them of the Act of Settlement.</hi> And <hi>May</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0. we find it moved in the Houſe, <hi>That nothing could be more advantageous to the King and Countrey, than to destroy the horrid barbarous act of Settlement; and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhall alledge the contrary, ſhall be deem'd an Enemy to both.</hi> Thereafter we find it mov'd by one of the Worthy Members of that Parliament, <hi>That the Act of Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould be publickly burnt by the Commons Hangman.</hi> Behold the tranſcendent care of King <hi>James,</hi> for the Priviledges and Properties of the Proteſtants, of <hi>Ireland!</hi> His accuſtomed Zeal obliges him at the firſt meeting of his <hi>packt-up Popiſh Parliament,</hi> to put them in mind of the beſt methods to Repeal the <hi>Great Security of he Proteſtants Eſtates.</hi> His impatience to have this done, could not ſtay till it had been propos'd by any of the Members themſelves; He muſt needs demonſtrat his tenderneſs to his <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lov'd Iriſh,</hi> by leading them the way how to break off the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Yoke, and make an inroad upon thoſe Properties the Proteſtants had acquired at the Expence of their Blood. As I intimated before, it was ever the Maxim of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Policy, to bridle in the unwearied Attempts of the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> for regaining their Countrey, by a good ſtanding Army in that Kingdom, conſiſting of Proteſtants: But here we have another Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of King <hi>James</hi>'s Care of the Proteſtants, in his turning out of all places in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, thoſe of that perſuaſion, to make room for others of his own Religion. It was the policy of all Nations to keep the people they had conquer'd, in as great ignorance of the <hi>Art of War,</hi> as poſſible, leſt ſome time or other they might ſhake off their Yoke, by a vigorous Rebellion. But King <hi>James</hi> inclin'd to take other meaſures, and be at the greateſt pains to teach an <hi>indocible Nation</hi> the uſe of Arms, that they might learn in due time to ſhake off the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government.</p>
            <p>As to the other part of the above-mentioned Aſſertion, <hi>That he had advanced ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of the Protestants in</hi> Ireland, <hi>to places both of the highest Honour and Truſt about his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as well as in his Army.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To paſs a juſt Judgment upon his Aſſertion, we need only conſider what ſort of perſons are at preſent about King <hi>James,</hi> both in <hi>Civil and Military Capacities,</hi> and we ſhall find it hard to meet with one ſingle perſon of the Proteſtant perſuaſion in the number. I could heartily wiſh, that all King <hi>James</hi> his Actions could as eaſily admit an excuſe as this; For the Authority aſſum'd upon Him by <hi>Monſieur d' Avaux</hi> and his other <hi>French Guardians,</hi> puts it almoſt beyond his power to employ <hi>Engliſh Roman Catholicks,</hi> far leſs <hi>Engliſh Protestants.</hi> At <hi>the Council-board</hi> we find none of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants. The Offices of Lord Lieutenant, Chancellor. Privy Seal, Secretary of State, Commiſſioners of the Treaſury, Lord Chief Juſtice, Sollicitor General, Attorney Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, and all the places of the Long Robe are enjoy'd by <hi>Roman Catholicks.</hi> As to Military Capacities, there is not one ſingle Gariſon, Fort, nor Caſtle within the whole Kingdom, except <hi>London-derry</hi> and <hi>Iniskilling,</hi> but are fill'd up with both popiſh Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors, Officers and Soldiers. In the Army, all the Field Officers are either <hi>French,</hi> or Native <hi>Iriſh</hi> of the ſame Religion: Yea, the <hi>French</hi>'s abſoluteneſs both at the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil-Board and the Army, has of late given the greateſt Jealouſie and Diſcontentment to ſome that have done King <hi>James</hi> the beſt ſervice.</p>
            <p>In the end of this firſt paragraph we are told, That King <hi>James, ly granting his Royal protection to ſuch, whoſe minds were ſhaken by the Arts of his Rebellious Subjects, has dispell'd their apprehenſions, and effectually ſecured them againſt the attempts even of their private Enemies.</hi> And then adds, <hi>His Ears have been always open to their juſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints: And ſo far has his Royal Mercy been extended to thoſe that were in Arms againſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41218:4"/>him, that he has actually pardoned ſeveral hundreds of them, and moſt notorious Criminals are kept in an eaſie Confinement.</hi> In reading this period, I find King <hi>James</hi> would Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon our Belief and Senſes ſomething as much contradictory to it left, as <hi>Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation;</hi> and the one as hard to be digeſted as the other. The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> tells us magiſterially, That albeit our Seeing, Feeling, Smeling, and Taſte, combine together, to aſſure us, that the Bread and Wine, is <hi>really ſuch,</hi> yet we muſt not give credit to theſe fallible Senſes of ours; but take it upon truſt from the Church, That what our Senſes tell us to be Bread and Wine, is quite another thing; and that there is nothing there left of any ſuch Elements, after once the prieſt has mumbled over <hi>the three Words.</hi> Thus, King <hi>James,</hi> having long accuſtomed himſelf to an <hi>Arbitrary power</hi> over our perſons and properties, when King; He cannot refrain from venturing an Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay of it upon our Reaſons and Senſes, even when he is laid aſide: For albeit out Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are continually entertained with hundreds of Objects, that bear in upon our Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, a certain perſwaſion that the poor proteſtants of <hi>Ireland,</hi> are every day flying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from that Countrey, at any rate to avoid the many Barbarities exerciſed upon them; and that that Kingdom is become the Scene of Miſery and Diſſolution; yet King <hi>James</hi> would have us wiſely lay aſide theſe mean helps of Senſe and Reaſon, and <hi>take it upon his bate Word,</hi> that there is no ſuch thing, which I think very few will be inclinable to do. If what is aſſerted upon this Subject be true, and conſequently our Senſes and Reaſon ſo ſtrangely beguiled. It neceſſarly behoves us to paſs no milder Judgment upon thoſe Noblemen, Biſhops, Gentlemen, and perſons of all ranks, that have left their Countrey, ſince King <hi>James</hi>'s arrival there, but that they are <hi>quite out of their wits:</hi> For what better Name can be given to perſons that have left their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, Eſtates and Employments, to become here the <hi>greateſt objects of Charity,</hi> when not only they might have been ſafe at home, but <hi>ſecured againſt the attempts of their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Enemies?</hi> In this Word <hi>private Enemies,</hi> we are obliged to King <hi>James</hi>'s Secreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry (whether our of Ignorance, or Deſign, <hi>I</hi> know not) for a fairly inſinuated diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Proteſtants in <hi>Ireland,</hi> their <hi>private</hi> and <hi>publick Enemies.</hi> We know that all <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks are tyed, by the Dictats of their Church, to be Enemies to proteſtants; and to extirpate them, when it comes in their power: And this, as flowing from a publick Intereſt of Religion, may juſtly be termed a <hi>publick Enmity;</hi> But the Natives of <hi>Ireland</hi> over and above that publick quarrel of Religion, have a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate one of Revenge, for recovering from the Proteſtants their Lands acquired by the Sword; and no age has paſſed ſince the Conqueſt of <hi>Ireland,</hi> but what has afforded bloody proofs of the revengful Spirit of that people, upon this ſcore. If <hi>free quarter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, plundering, robbing, diſarming, ſeizing on Eſtates, impriſoning, murdering in cold Blood,</hi> and the lik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>be a ſecuring theſe poor Protestants againſt their private Enemies,</hi> they have no reaſon to complain of King <hi>James</hi> his conduct: But alas! to be ruin'd, and in the mean time to ſee the Authors of it boldly affirm, that they do us all the Offices of kindneſs, is the hardeſt of Fates. I would fain know where are theſe hundreds that he has pardoned; for thoſe that flee every day from that unhappy Countrey, cannot inſtance us a ſingle one of them: And for theſe that are kept in ſuch <hi>eaſie Confinements,</hi> their condition, of all men, is moſt deplorable, ſeing they ly at the Mercy of an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, that waits but for a favourable juncture, to Sacrifice them to their Revenge. What ſort of <hi>ſecuring</hi> the Proteſtants of <hi>Ireland</hi> meet with, againſt their <hi>private Enemies;</hi> and what is the ordinary effect of <hi>protections</hi> given to theſe poor credulous people, will appear by this one inſtruce, among thouſands of others, of a protection given to a Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer in the County of <hi>Antr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m,</hi> in theſe Words, <hi>I</hi> Richard Hamilton, <hi>Lieutenant-General of his Majeſties Forces in</hi> U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſter, <hi>do hereby receive into his Majeſties protection, the Body and Goods of</hi> James Hunter <hi>of</hi> Bully menach <hi>in the County of</hi> Antrim, <hi>Yeoman; and do
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41218:5"/>promiſe and oblige my ſelf that none of the Army ſhall moleſt and hurt him, or take any thing from him. Given</hi> &amp;c. The poor <hi>protected Man,</hi> thus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oos'd, returns of his Houſe, and follows his labour; but anone down comes upon him the Rabble of the Army, like an inundation of <hi>Goths</hi> and <hi>Vandals;</hi> ſweep all before them, and leaves nothing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them, but a <hi>ſtarving Family.</hi> The wretched man making his addreſs to <hi>Hamilton,</hi> received this cold anſwer; <hi>I promiſed to protect you from the Army, but I have no power to reſtrain the Rabble.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the beginning of the ſecond Paragraph, we are told <hi>of the Care King</hi> James <hi>has taken of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>that they be not diſturbed in the exerciſe of their Religion, and poſſeſſion of their Benefices; and that all Proteſtant Diſſenters enjoy Liberty of their Conſciences, without the leaſt moleſtation. And out of his Royal Care for the proſperity of his People</hi> (as he calls them) <hi>he has recommended to his Parliament, as the first thing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be diſpatched, to ſettle ſuch a ſecurity and Liberty, both in Spiritual and Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Matters, as may put an end to theſe Diviſions, which have been the ſource of all their Miſeries; being reſolved, as much as in him lies, to entail Liberty and Happineſs on his People ſo far, as to put it out of the power of his Succeſſors, to invade the one, or revenge the other: And this, he takes God to witneſs, was always his deſign.</hi> The firſt part of this long period, is but a repetition of what had been formerly ſaid, in the firſt Paragraph, <hi>of the Proteſtants, their Religion, Priviledges, and Properties being his chief Care;</hi> and what truth, that can bear, we have ſhewed already. There is one thing, that <hi>I</hi> find King <hi>James</hi> was ever inclinable to value himſelf upon, and which he here likewiſe men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; <hi>I mean, his tenderneſs to Proteſtant Diſſenters,</hi> and his Principle for <hi>Liberty of Conſcience.</hi> They are very thick ſighted, that could not diſcern what lay at the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of this Liberty, and what could be the true motive that ſhould have induced one of King <hi>James</hi>'s Religion to do it? But becauſe he has been at the pains, ſo often, during his Reign, to aſſure us, That it was his Opinion, Conſcience ſhould not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained, nor People forced in Matters of Religion; and particularly in his Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for Liberty of Conſcience, dated <hi>Auguſt</hi> 4. 1687. I'll beg leave to ſay, That in this, King <hi>James</hi> is no obedient Son of the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> for it has, over, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver again, decreed the <hi>extirpation of Hereticks:</hi> It encourages Princes to it, by the offer of the Pardon of their Sins: It threatens them to it, by denouncing to them not only the Judgments of God, but that which is often more ſenſible, the loſs of their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions. It's true, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> tells us, <hi>The Church does not always execute her power of depoſing Heretical Princes, though ſhe always retains it;</hi> and he gives a very good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for it, <hi>becauſe ſhe is not at all times in a capacity to put it in Execution:</hi> So the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſame Reaſon, might have made it unadviſeable to King <hi>James,</hi> when he was ſo libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of his Tolerations, to extirpate Hereſie, becauſe it could not be then eaſily done: But we ſee the Right remains intire, and is put in execution, in ſuch an unrelenting manner in our neighbouring Countries, that it has a very Grace, to ſee any Member of that Church pretend to be againſt <hi>conſtraining the Conſcience,</hi> in point of Religion: And when we conſider, that neither the Policy and true Intereſt of <hi>France,</hi> nor the greatneſs of their Monarch, could withſtand theſe bloody Counſels, that are indeed parts of that Religion; I could never ſee any reaſon to induce us to believe, that the late Tolerations of Religion were propoſed with any other deſign, but either to divide the Proteſtants among themſelves, or to lay them aſleep, till it was time to give the alarm for deſtroying them. And that in the Opinion of that Church, the Glory of extirpating Hereſie, is valued above all other great Actions, we have a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable inſtance in that famous Harrangue made by the Biſhop of <hi>Violence,</hi> to the <hi>French King</hi> in the Name of the <hi>Convention of the</hi> French <hi>Clergy at St.</hi> Germans, in <hi>June</hi> 1684, where that Prelate having recounted the innumerable Converſions made by the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41218:5"/>Kings Orders, Cares, and Liberalities, to uſe his very Words; he ſubſumes thus: <hi>Je bien même, que chercherois vainement dans les ſicoles paſſés, que l'appulerois vainement a mon ſecours, touts les eloges des p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>miers, &amp; des plus ſaints Empereurs.</hi> It were, <hi>ſays he,</hi> in vain to ſearch into the Ages paſt; It were in vain to call to my aſſiſtance all the Panegyricks of the firſt and holieſt of the Emperours: And afterwards he treats him with the Title of the Great Restorer of the Faith, and extirpator of Hereſie; and tells him, that theſe infinitely ſurmount all his other glorious Titles. And then ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Maſters great Victories in <hi>Germany, Flanders,</hi> &amp;c. and the Peace of <hi>Nimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guen,</hi> made upon the back of them, he concludes thus: That the Fruit, which the King had received by that Peace, made it fully apparent, what was the principal end he aimed at, in the Victories; meaning, the Extirpation of Hereticks. The late King <hi>James,</hi> has always copied ſo fair after <hi>Lewis le Grand,</hi> That we have no Reaſon to queſtion, but in this ſo glorious a work, of extirpating Hereſie, it would have come up to the Original, if his Deſigns, and a favourable juncture of time had concurr'd to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
            <p>When he tells us, <hi>That the firſt thing he has recommended to his Parliament, is, to ſettle ſuch a Security and Liberty, as may put an end to theſe Diviſions, which have been the ſource of all our Miſeries,</hi> I find the greateſt exactneſs of Truth, in theſe Words, if we but take them in the ſence and meaning of the Speaker, <hi>viz.</hi> a <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> Prince. For, albeit we all know, that the firſt thing recommended by King <hi>James,</hi> to his <hi>Iriſh</hi> Parliament, was, The Repealing the <hi>Act of Settlement;</hi> which is, indeed, the Great Charter, by which moſt of the Proteſtants enjoy their Eſtates: And tho' the deſtroying that <hi>Act,</hi> gives a mortal blow to the Proteſtant Intereſt in <hi>Ireland;</hi> yet, according to the native Principles of King <hi>James</hi> his Religion, the repealing of this <hi>Act of Settlement,</hi> may well be called, <hi>The ſetling a Security, that may put an end to their Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, which has been the ſource of all our Miſeries:</hi> That is to ſay, King <hi>James,</hi> from a Principle of Religion, is reſolved to remove that Barrier, that protects the Proteſtants in <hi>Ireland,</hi> in their Separation from the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> That by its removal, he may be in a capacity conform to the Holy Dictates of that Church, and the laudable Example of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. to put an end to all Diviſions in point of Religion, by forcing them to return to the Mother Church, by the <hi>calm Methods</hi> of late ſo happily uſed in <hi>France.</hi> And this, I am very inclinable to believe, he may, with a ſafe Conſcience take God to Witneſs, was always his Deſign. I am ſomething ſurprized to hear King <hi>James</hi> his Secretaries, put out their Maſters ſecret Deſigns, that were ſo much his Intereſt to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal; but the Truth is, we knew them before, to our Coſt; and we hope, are on the way, to be ſufficiently ſecured againſt any further Effects of them.</p>
            <p>In the end of this Paragraph, we are told, <hi>That ſeveral Proteſtants, are now returned to their Country and Habitations; and that more would follow, if the Ports were open: But the Uſurpers</hi> (as he pleaſes to call their preſent Majeſties) <hi>know too well the Sincerity of his intentions, to permit ſo free Paſſage for them.</hi> This, indeed, is all of a piece with the reſt. We are Witneſſes, every Day, of hundreds of poor Proteſtants of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, graſping every Opportunity, they can at any rate purchaſe, to abandon their Homes, and all that's dear to them, that they may but eſcape with their Lives: And I defie any of King <hi>James</hi> his Friends, to inſtance me one ſingle Perſon, of any Condition, that have dared to return Home, ſince his Arrival in <hi>Ireland;</hi> none of them being ſo far in love with Deſtruction, as to venture on his Protection. In this Epithet, King <hi>James</hi> is pleaſed to beſtow on their Majeſties, he imitates his Patron, <hi>Louis le Grand;</hi> who, I confeſs, has the greateſt Reaſon of Hatred againſt his Majeſty, as being the great Supporter of the Liberty of <hi>Europe;</hi> and who, in conjunction with his Allies, is beſt able to bring to Reaſon, that inſupportable Enemy of <hi>Chriſtendom;</hi> yea, of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:41218:6"/>it ſelf. It were an impertinent piece of Boldneſs, or rather, unpardonable Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence, to offer to vindicate their Majeſties from that injurious Deſignation; ſince the Wiſdom and Power of the Parliament, is paramount to all private aſſertions of their Majeſties juſt Right: And that the moſt, if not all the Crowned Heads, and Soveraign Princes, and States of <hi>Europe,</hi> not only rank our preſent King, among the beſt and greateſt Kings of <hi>England;</hi> but promiſe to themſelves, from his Aſſiſtance, to bridle <hi>Louis le Grand</hi> within his proper Boundaries. It was ever looked upon as a Principle of common Law; That an Heir in Remainder, has juſt Cauſe to ſue him that is in Poſſeſſion, if he makes Waſtes on the Inheritance that belongs to him in Rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. That the Heir of a Crown ſhould interpoſe, when he ſees him that is in Poſſeſſion, hurried on by bad Counſels, to ſubject an independent Kingdom, to a Foreign Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, is much more reaſonable, ſince the thing is of much more Importance; and that this was King <hi>James</hi> his Caſe, is apparent, by the Tranſactions of the Earl of <hi>Caſtlemain</hi> at the Court of <hi>Rome;</hi> and the rather, that by a great many Statutes, it was Treaſon to have Correſpondence with that See: This inclined to the ſetting up of a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Heir, in ſuch a manner, as the whole Kingdom believed him ſuppoſititious, was a juſt and lawful Ground for one Sovereign Prince (ſuch as his Majeſty was when Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>) to make War againſt another, that had ſo abuſed his Power; and 'tis an unqueſtionable Maxim among Lawyers, <hi>That the Succeſs of a just War, gives a lawful Title to that which is acquired in the Progreſs of it.</hi> Therefore, King <hi>James</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo far ſunk in the War, that he both abandoned his People, and deſerted the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, all his Right and Title to the Crown did thereupon accrue to his preſent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, in the <hi>Right</hi> of <hi>Conqueſt:</hi> So that he might have lawfully then aſſumed the Crown: But his preſent Majeſty choſe rather to leave the matter to the determination of the Peers and Repreſentatives of the People, aſſembled with all Freedom in the Convention, who did thereupon declare him King; ſo that, tho' he was veſted with a juſt Title of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, he choſe rather to receive the Crown by their Declaration, than to hold it in the Right of his ſword. This I thought fit to ſay, not ſo much for Confutation of the inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry done their Majeſties in the above-mentioned Deſignation, which needs not my Pen; but to ſtate their Right to the Crown in ſuch a Light, as may remove needleſs ſcruples of ſwearing Allegiance to them.</p>
            <p>In the beginning of the third and laſt Paragraph, King <hi>James</hi> tell us, <hi>That nothing but his own Inclinations to juſtice, could prevail with him to ſuch a Proceeding, as that of his care of his Proteſtant Subjects in</hi> Ireland; <hi>and hopes his Protestant Subjects in</hi> England, (as he calls them) <hi>will make a Judgment of what they may expect from him.</hi> Indeed, it is no difficult Matter, to make a Judgment of what we may juſtly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from him, if ever Divine Judgement, as the Reward of our Ingratitude for ſo great a Deliverance, ſhould permit us to fall again under the heavy Yoke of a Popiſh Prince, whom we have ſo juſtly and happily thrown off. King <hi>James</hi> is of a Religion, that has, in a famous Council, decreed, That <hi>no Faith is to be kept with Hereticks;</hi> much leſs with Subjects, that he looks upon, as ſo many <hi>Rebels;</hi> and will not miſs to treat them as ſuch, when ever they give him the Opportunity of doing it. For his greateſt Admirers do not run to that height of Idolatry, to imagine him ſo much <hi>Angel,</hi> as not to take all Methods to revenge ſuch an Affront, and ſecure himſelf at our Coſt, from ſuch Treatment for the future. The Apprehenſions of which Reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment would ſtrike ſuch Terror in Men's Minds, that nothing would be capable to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert them from offering up <hi>All,</hi> for an Atonement; and <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Slavery</hi> will be thought a good Bargain, if they can but ſave their Lives. Then we might lament our Miſeries, when it ſhould be out of our Power to help them; for a <hi>Prince</hi> of Orange, is not always ready to reſcue us, with ſo vaſt expence, and hazard of his Perſon.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41218:6"/>And I muſt ſay, if ever our Madneſs ſhould hurry us thus far, we ſhould become rather the Objects of Laughter, than of Pity.</p>
            <p>Therefore, King <hi>James promiſes and declares, That nothing ſhall ever alter his Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions to purſue ſuch, and no other methods, as by his ſaid Subjects in Parliament, ſhall be found proper for their common Security, peace and happineſs.</hi> Such filly bates as theſe will not now take; and here is a great deal of Pains loſt, to perſwade us to rely upon Promiſes, ſo often made already, and as often broken. What Adjournments, Proro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, and Diſſolutions of Parliament, we have had of late, is not eaſie to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten. We have found, to our ſad Experience, that the Intereſt of the Court, and that of the People, were two incompatible things; and to endeavour a Redreſs of the leaſt Grievance, <hi>in a Parliamentary way,</hi> was not only a vain Attempt, but a deſign, branded with the infamous Name of <hi>Diſſatisfaction to the Government.</hi> I need not be at the pains to repeat all the Promiſes made by King <hi>James,</hi> of the ſame Nature with this in his Declaration; and how well they were obſerved, we all know. Yet I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but take notice of <hi>one,</hi> made in his firſt Speech to his Privy-Council, an hour af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Brother's Death, printed by his own Command, in theſe Words: <hi>My Lords, before I enter on any other, I think fit to ſay ſomething to you, ſince it has pleaſed Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God to place me in this Station; and I'm now to ſucceed to ſo good and gracious a King, as well as ſo very kind a Brother. I think fit to declare to you, That I will endeavour to follow his Example; and moſt eſpecially, in that of his great Clemency and Tenderneſs to his People.</hi> I <hi>have been reported to be a Man for Arbitrary Power; but that is not the only thing, that has been ſaid of me: And I ſhal endeavour to preſerve this Government, both in Church and State, as it is now by Law eſtabliſhed. I know, the Principle of the Church of</hi> England <hi>is for Monarchy, and the Members thereof have ſhown themſelves good and loyal Subjects; therefore</hi> I <hi>ſhall always take care to defend and ſupport it. I know the Laws of</hi> England <hi>are ſufficient to make the King as great a Monarch as I can wiſh: And as I ſhal never depart from the juſt Rights and Prerogatives of the Crown, ſo I ſhal never invade any Man's Property.</hi> He that can reconcile this Speech, with King <hi>James</hi> his after-Actings, is the fitteſt Perſon I know, to explain the Popiſh Notion, of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour's Body being in a thouſand diſtinct Places at once. In theſe Expreſſions, he takes it very unkindly to have been reported a Man for Arbitrary Power, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes a great many things, that are contradictory to it; but how well he deſerved the Character, all his Conduct has made it appear with a Witneſs.</p>
            <p>We have one of the moſt remarkable inſtances of King <hi>James</hi>'s being againſt Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Power, in this Declaration of the 12th of <hi>February</hi> 1686/7,<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for a <hi>Toleration in Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> where we find theſe new coin'd Words, thrice made uſe of, <hi>Our Abſolute Power;</hi> with this addition, <hi>Which all our Subjects are to obey without Reſerve.</hi> Now <hi>Abſolute</hi> in its natural Signification, importing the being without all ties and reſtraints; then the true meaning of this, ſeems to be, That there is an inherent Power in the King, which can neither be reſtrained by Laws, Promiſes, nor Oaths, for nothing leſs, than being free from all theſe, renders a Power Abſolute. Though the Term <hi>Abſolute</hi> was enough to ſtretch our Allegiance; yet that which comes after, is yet a ſtep of an higher Nature, tho' one can hardly imagine, what can go beyond <hi>Abſolute Power,</hi> and 'tis in theſe Words, <hi>which all our Subjects are to obey, without Reſerve.</hi> This in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, the carrying Obedience many degrees beyond what the Grand Seignior yet ever claimed; for the moſt deſpotick Princes in the World, before <hi>Lewis le Grand</hi>'s time, thought it enough to oblige their Subjects to ſubmit to their Power, and to <hi>bear</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they thought fit to impoſe upon them: But, till the fatal Days of the Dragoon. Converſions, it was never ſo much as pretended, that Subjects were bound to obey their Princes, <hi>without Reſerve;</hi> and to be of his Religion, becauſe he would have it
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41218:7"/>ſo; the only convincing Argument uſed by theſe <hi>booted Apoſtles</hi> of late. So, without doubt, this Qualification of the Duty of Subjects, was induſtriouſly put in here by King <hi>James</hi> his Jeſuitick Counſels, to prepare the Proteſtants of <hi>Scotland</hi> for a terrible <hi>Le Roy le vent,</hi> ſince the poor Pretenſions of the Conſcience, Honour, Religion, and Reaſon, would have been reckoned as <hi>Reſerves</hi> upon their Obedience; which were all, by the Expreſſions, ſhut out.</p>
            <p>Before I leave this Paramount Inſtance of King <hi>James</hi>'s aſſuming to himſelf an <hi>Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Power,</hi> beyond what the Great <hi>Turk</hi> claims, and contrary to his own reiterated promiſes, I muſt take notice of another very <hi>comprehenſive expreſſion</hi> in that ſame De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration for a Toleration in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and it's this. <q rend="margQuotes">'We think fit to declare, That we will not ſuffer Violence to be offered to any Man's Conſcience, nor will we uſe force or INVINCIBLE NECESSITY upon any Man, on the account of his Perſwaſion, nor the Proteſtant Religion.'</q> When I firſt read theſe Words, I eaſily perceiv'd what caution was uſed in the choice of them; for it is clear, the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Words of <hi>Violence</hi> and <hi>Force,</hi> are to be explained and determined by theſe laſt, of <hi>INVINCIBLE NECESSITY:</hi> So that King <hi>James</hi> very wiſely promiſed only, to lay no invincible Neceſſity on his Subjects; but for all <hi>Neceſſities</hi> that were not <hi>Invincible,</hi> they might expect to have felt a large ſhare of them. For Diſgraces, want of Imployment, Finings, Impriſonments, and even Death it ſelf, are all <hi>Vincible</hi> things to a Man of a firmneſs of Mind; yea, the Violence of Torture, the Furies of Dragoons, and the Precedents uſed of late in <hi>France,</hi> might have been fairly included within this Promiſe, ſince a great and ſublime Soul, fortified with an extraordinary meaſure of Grace, might be able to ſupport under them.</p>
            <p>Now, ſince we have had ſo many experiences of King <hi>James</hi>'s faithfulneſs to his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, before he abandoned the Government, I pray, what Arguments has he of late given us, that he will be more obſerving of his Word, than hitherto he has been. Sure the reducing Hereticks to the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> is no leſs Meritorious than before; nor King <hi>James,</hi> by breathing a little of the <hi>French Air,</hi> and <hi>concerting Meaſures</hi> with <hi>Lewis</hi> the Fourteenth, become leſs Bigot.</p>
            <p>King <hi>James</hi> concludes his Declaration with <hi>aſſuring all his pretended Subjects, That if, within twenty days after his appearing in perſon within</hi> England, <hi>they return to their O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, by deſerting his Enemies, and joining with him, he will grant them his full pardon, and all paſt miſcarriages ſhall be forgot.</hi> This merits no other Anſwer, but what has been already ſaid. Only this, he muſt have the worſt Opinion of the frailty of Humane Nature, that can be brought to believe, That any Man, not altogether di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted of his Reaſon, can be prevailed with, to join King <hi>James,</hi> though he were in <hi>England,</hi> except he be of that Religion that obliges him to aſſiſt a Prince, that ſets up ſo fairly for the Glorious Title of the <hi>Extirpator of Hereſie;</hi> and to venture all upon the uncertainty of ſeeing their Church Triumphant. And if there be any of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Perſwaſion, ſo ſtrangely infatuated, as but to wiſh his Return, I ſhall entertain them with no other Anſwer, but the recommending to them that place of Holy Writ, Preached upon before the Houſe of Commons, of late, by an eminent Divine, <hi>Ezra.</hi> 9. <hi>ch. v.</hi> 13.14. <q rend="margQuotes">'And after all that is come upon us, for our evil deeds, and for our great treſpaſs, ſeing that thou our God haſt puniſhed us leſs than our Iniquities de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, and haft given us ſuch a Deliverance as this: Should we again break thy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, and joyn in affinity with the People of theſe abominations; would'ſt not thou be angry with us, till thou hadſt conſumed us, ſo that there ſhould be no remnant, nor eſcaping?</q>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed at <hi>London,</hi> and Re-Printed at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> 1689.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:41218:7"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
